<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cut query | Sagnik Mukhopadhyay</title>
    <link>https://sagnikm.github.io/tag/cut-query/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://sagnikm.github.io/tag/cut-query/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Cut query</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://sagnikm.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Cut query</title>
      <link>https://sagnikm.github.io/tag/cut-query/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cut query algorithms with star contraction</title>
      <link>https://sagnikm.github.io/publication/focs2022a/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sagnikm.github.io/publication/focs2022a/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We study the complexity of determining the edge connectivity of a simple graph with cut queries.
We show that (i) there is a bounded-error randomized  algorithm that computes edge connectivity with $O(n)$ cut queries, and (ii) there is a bounded-error quantum algorithm that computes edge connectivity with $\tilde O(\sqrt{n})$ cut queries. To prove these results we introduce a new technique, called &lt;em&gt;star contraction&lt;/em&gt;, to randomly contract edges of a graph while preserving non-trivial minimum cuts.  In star contraction vertices randomly contract an edge incident on a small set of randomly chosen &amp;lsquo;center&amp;rsquo; vertices.  In contrast to the related 2-out contraction technique of Ghaffari, Nowicki, and Thorup [SODA&#39;20], star contraction only contracts vertex-disjoint star subgraphs, which allows it to be efficiently implemented via cut queries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The $O(n)$ bound from item (i) was not known even for the simpler problem of connectivity, and it improves the $O(n \log^3 n)$ upper bound by Rubinstein, Schramm, and Weinberg [ITCS&#39;18]. The bound is tight under the reasonable conjecture that the randomized communication complexity of connectivity is $\Omega(n \log n)$, an open question since the seminal work of Babai, Frankl, and Simon [FOCS&#39;86]. The bound also excludes using edge connectivity on simple graphs to prove a superlinear randomized query lower bound for minimizing a symmetric submodular function. The quantum algorithm from item~(ii) gives a nearly-quadratic separation with the randomized complexity, and addresses an open question of Lee, Santha, and Zhang [SODA&#39;21]. The algorithm can alternatively be viewed as computing the edge connectivity of a simple graph with $\tilde O(\sqrt{n})$ matrix-vector multiplication queries to its adjacency matrix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we demonstrate the use of star contraction outside of the cut query setting by designing a one-pass semi-streaming algorithm for computing edge connectivity in the complete vertex arrival setting. This contrasts with the edge arrival setting where two passes are required.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
