<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Complexity theory | Sagnik Mukhopadhyay</title>
    <link>https://sagnikm.github.io/tag/complexity-theory/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://sagnikm.github.io/tag/complexity-theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Complexity theory</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://sagnikm.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Complexity theory</title>
      <link>https://sagnikm.github.io/tag/complexity-theory/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards Understanding Challenges of Computation over Large Network</title>
      <link>https://sagnikm.github.io/project/graphcom/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sagnikm.github.io/project/graphcom/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;hiring&#34;&gt;Hiring!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am looking for a motivated and mathematically inclined PhD student
with previous experience in courses/modules in theoretical computer science.
This position is based in the Department of Computer Science in the University
of Sheffield and comes with full tuition fee and stipend. Travel support is also
available. The potential candidate will be expected to support algorithms teaching
in the department (which will be paid additionally).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A strong interest in graph algorithms, complexity theory, distributed and
streaming algorithms and/or combinatorial optimization will be a
plus. Starting date is negotiable. Please see below for a brief motivation and
papers of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;motivation&#34;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After a long-drawn war, two nations, Oceania and Eurasia,
are now at peace but in not much of talking terms. However,
they will have to figure out how much shipment their
combined rail network can carry from the capital city of
Oceania to that of Eurasia. Both Oceania and Eurasia know
about their own rail networks in detail, but none of them
knows anything about other nation&amp;rsquo;s network plans. Because
of the political situation, they want to keep communication
between them to a minimum. You are the chief researcher of
Eurasia, in contact with Winston Smith, the chief researcher
of Oceania. How much communication do you need to do to
figure it out?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this project is to investigate such fundamental
network problems where the network data is distributed
between multiple processors. Such problems appear in
countless guises in modern life: The transportation problem
mentioned before is inspired by actual logistic
difficulties that kept the US and Russia busy during the
first half of the 20th century (see
&lt;a href=&#34;https://tinyurl.com/2p844c2y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://tinyurl.com/2p844c2y&lt;/a&gt; for a fun read). In the modern
realm of data explosion, these network questions are more
topical than ever: The network data (think of the friendship
network of Facebook or the follower network of Twitter or
the hyperlink network of Google) is usually too large to be
stored in a single computational processor and hence is
generally distributed among a large number of
processors/servers who need to communicate with each other
via a network in order to perform various computational tasks.
This problem is generally addressed via different storage
architectures for fast access and efficient software
paradigms such as MapReduce, Hadoop, and Spark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many traditional algorithms that were widely used in the
past have become greatly inefficient in practice for such
distributed systems. The main goal of the proposed research
is to design (or prove the hardness of) fundamental network
algorithms and their generalisations in such distributed
models of computation. To be concrete, we will mainly be
interested in the following two models in this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two-party communication protocols: The graph data is distributed to two machines, namely Alice and Bob. Machines can access their local data for free, but it costs for them to communicate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Query protocols: The graph data is stored in external memory (e.g., among many external servers or cloud) and the local machine is allowed to access the data only by query accesses which can be answered quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project will lead to major advances in our understanding of &amp;ldquo;distributed
network algorithms&amp;rdquo;, which is an important research area within theoretical
computer science that is concerned with addressing precisely the question
described above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-few-papers-of-interest&#34;&gt;A few papers of interest&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Li Chen, Rasmus Kyng, Yang P. Liu, Richard Peng, Maximilian Probst Gutenberg, Sushant Sachdeva
Maximum Flow and Minimum-Cost Flow in Almost-Linear Time
PDF: &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.00671&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.00671&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haotian Jiang:
Minimizing Convex Functions with Integral Minimizers. SODA 2021: 976-985
PDF: &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.01445&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.01445&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicholas J. A. Harvey:
Matroid intersection, pointer chasing, and Young&amp;rsquo;s seminormal representation of Sn. SODA 2008: 542-549
PDF:  &lt;a href=&#34;https://dl-acm-org.focus.lib.kth.se/citation.cfm?id=1347142&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://dl-acm-org.focus.lib.kth.se/citation.cfm?id=1347142&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrei Graur, Tristan Pollner, Vidhya Ramaswamy, S. Matthew Weinberg:
New Query Lower Bounds for Submodular Function Minimization. ITCS 2020: 64:1-64:16
PDF: &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.06889&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.06889&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yu Chen, Sanjeev Khanna, Ansh Nagda:
Near-linear Size Hypergraph Cut Sparsifiers. FOCS 2020: 61-72
PDF: &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.04992&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.04992&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chandra Chekuri, Chao Xu:
Minimum Cuts and Sparsification in Hypergraphs. SIAM J. Comput. 47(6): 2118-2156 (2018)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sagnik Mukhopadhyay, Danupon Nanongkai:
Weighted Min-Cut: Sequential, Cut-Query and Streaming Algorithms. CoRR abs/1911.01651 (2019)
PDF: &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.01651&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.01651&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S. Apers and T. Lee
Quantum complexity of minimum cut.
PDF: &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2011.09823&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2011.09823&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noam Nisan, Avi Wigderson: Rounds in Communication Complexity Revisited. SIAM J. Comput. 22(1): 211-219 (1993)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noam Nisan: The Demand Query Model for Bipartite Matching: SODA 2021: 592-599&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
