<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Min-cut | Sagnik Mukhopadhyay</title>
    <link>https://sagnikm.github.io/tag/min-cut/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://sagnikm.github.io/tag/min-cut/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Min-cut</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://sagnikm.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Min-cut</title>
      <link>https://sagnikm.github.io/tag/min-cut/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Faster Connectivity in Low-Rank Hypergraphs via Expander Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://sagnikm.github.io/publication/hypergraph_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sagnikm.github.io/publication/hypergraph_preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We design an algorithm for computing connectivity in hypergraphs which runs in time $\hat O_r(p + \min{\lambda n^2, n^r/\lambda})$, where $p$ is the size, $n$ is the number of vertices, $r$ is the rank (size of the largest hyperedge), and $\lambda$ is the connectivity of the hypergraph. The $\hat O_r(\cdot)$ hides terms that are subpolynomial in the main parameter and terms that depend only on $r$. Our algorithm is faster than existing algorithms when the connectivity $\lambda$ is $\Omega(n^{(r-2)/2})$.
The heart of our algorithm is a structural result regarding min-cuts in simple hypergraphs. We show a trade-off between the number of hyperedges taking part in all min-cuts and the size of the smaller side of the min-cut. This structural result can be viewed as a generalization of a well-known structural theorem for simple graphs [Kawarabayashi-Thorup, JACM 19].  We extend the framework of expander decomposition to simple hypergraphs in order to prove this structural result. We also make the proof of the structural result constructive to obtain our faster hypergraph connectivity algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Work-Optimal Parallel Minimum Cuts for Non-Sparse Graphs</title>
      <link>https://sagnikm.github.io/publication/spaa2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sagnikm.github.io/publication/spaa2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We present the first work-optimal polylogarithmic-depth parallel algorithm for the minimum cut problem on non-sparse graphs. For $m\geq n^{1+\epsilon}$ for any constant $\epsilon&amp;gt;0$, our algorithm requires $O(m \log n)$ work and $O(\log^3 n)$ depth and succeeds with high probability.
Its work matches the best $O(m \log n)$ runtime for sequential algorithms [MN STOC’20; GMW SOSA&#39;21].  This improves the previous best work by Geissmann and Gianinazzi [SPAA&#39;18] by $O(\log^3 n)$ factor, while matching the depth of their algorithm. To do this, we design a work-efficient approximation algorithm and parallelize the recent sequential algorithms [MN STOC&#39;21; GMW SOSA&#39;21] that exploit a connection between 2-respecting minimum cuts and 2-dimensional orthogonal range searching.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Weighted Min-Cut in Nearly-Optimal Time</title>
      <link>https://sagnikm.github.io/publication/stoc2021a/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sagnikm.github.io/publication/stoc2021a/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Minimum-weight cut (min-cut) is a basic measure of a network&amp;rsquo;s connectivity strength. While the min-cut can be computed efficiently in the sequential setting [Karger STOC&#39;96], there was no efficient way for a distributed network to compute its own min-cut without limiting the input structure or dropping the output quality: In the standard CONGEST model, existing algorithms with nearly-optimal time (e.g. [Ghaffari, Kuhn, DISC&#39;13; Nanongkai, Su, DISC&#39;14]) can guarantee a solution that is $(1+\epsilon)$-approximation at best while the exact $\tilde O(n^{0.8} D^{0.2} + n^{0.9})$-time algorithm [Ghaffari, Nowicki, Thorup, SODA&#39;20] works only on &lt;em&gt;simple&lt;/em&gt; networks (no weights and no parallel edges). Throughout, $n$ and $D$ denote the network&amp;rsquo;s number of vertices and hop-diameter, respectively. For the weighted case, the best bound was $\tilde O(n)$ [Daga, Henzinger, Nanongkai, Saranurak, STOC&#39;19].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we provide an {\em exact} $\tilde O(\sqrt n + D)$-time algorithm for computing min-cut on &lt;em&gt;weighted&lt;/em&gt; networks. Our result improves even the previous algorithm that works only on simple networks. Its time complexity matches the known lower bound up to polylogarithmic factors.
At the heart of our algorithm are a clever routing trick and two structural lemmas regarding the structure of a minimum cut of a graph. These two structural lemmas considerably strengthen and generalize the framework of Mukhopadhyay-Nanongkai [STOC&#39;20] and can be of independent interest.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weighted Min-Cut: Sequential, Cut-Query and Streaming Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://sagnikm.github.io/publication/stoc2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sagnikm.github.io/publication/stoc2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Consider the following &lt;em&gt;2-respecting min-cut&lt;/em&gt; problem. Given a weighted graph $G$ and its spanning tree $T$, find the minimum cut among the cuts that contain at most two edges in $T$. This problem is an important subroutine in Karger&amp;rsquo;s celebrated randomized near-linear-time min-cut algorithm [STOC&#39;96]. We present a new approach for this problem which can be easily implemented in many settings, leading to the following randomized min-cut algorithms for weighted graphs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An $O\left(m\frac{\log^2 n}{\log\log n} + n\log^6 n\right)$-time sequential algorithm: This improves Karger&amp;rsquo;s long-standing $O(m \log^3 n)$ and $O\left(m\frac{(\log^2 n)\log (n^2/m)}{\log\log n} + n\log^6 n\right)$ bounds when the input graph is not extremely sparse or dense. Improvements over Karger&amp;rsquo;s bounds were previously known only under a rather strong assumption that the input graph is {\em simple} (unweighted without parallel edges) [Henzinger, Rao, Wang, SODA&#39;17; Ghaffari, Nowicki, Thorup, SODA&#39;20]. For unweighted graphs  (possibly with parallel edges) and using bit operations, our bound can be further improved to $O\left(m\frac{\log^{1.5} n}{\log\log n} + n\log^6 n\right)$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An algorithm that requires $\tilde O(n)$ &lt;em&gt;cut queries&lt;/em&gt; to compute the min-cut of a weighted graph: This answers an open problem by Rubinstein, Schramm, and Weinberg [ITCS&#39;18], who obtained a similar bound for simple graphs. Our bound is tight up to polylogarithmic factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;streaming&lt;/em&gt; algorithm that requires $\tilde O(n)$ space and $O(\log n)$ passes to compute the min-cut: The only previous non-trivial exact min-cut algorithm in this setting is the 2-pass $\tilde O(n)$-space algorithm on simple graphs [Rubenstein et al. ITCS 2018] observed by Assadi, Chen, and Khanna [STOC&#39;19]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to Karger&amp;rsquo;s 2-respecting min-cut algorithm which deploys sophisticated dynamic programming techniques, our approach exploits some cute structural properties so that it only needs to compute the values of $\tilde O(n)$ cuts corresponding to removing $\tilde O(n)$ pairs of tree edges, an operation that can be done quickly in many settings.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
